<ndz_document>
  <ndz_title>Off-Axis Field of a Current Loop</ndz_title>
  <ndz_author>Eric Dennison</ndz_author>
  <ndz_date>03/26/2004</ndz_date>
  <ndz_abstract>
  This simple formula can be obtained using the 
  <a href="../basics?biotsavart">law of biot savart</a>, integrated over
  a circular current loop to obtain the magnetic field at any point in
  space.  Compare this to the much simpler formula for calculating the 
  <a href="../solenoids/?currloop">on-axis magnetic field due to a current
  loop</a>. Please visit the 
  <a href="https://www.wakari.io/sharing/bundle/ericdennison/magnets/Off%20Axis%20Field%20of%20a%20Current%20Loop.ipynb">
  iPython Notebook on Off-Axis Field of a Current Loop</a> for additional
  information and software examples of this topic.
  </ndz_abstract>
  <ndz_section type="picture" title="">
    <ndz_image type="svg" name="offaxisloop" file="offaxisloop.svg" alt="Off-axis field of a current loop" />
  </ndz_section>
  <ndz_section type="eqn" title="Axial, Radial Components">
    <ndz_image type="tex" name="equation1" alt="Off-axis field, axial component">
    B_x = B_0\frac{1}{\pi\sqrt{Q}}\left[E(k)\frac{1-\alpha^2-\beta^2}{Q-4\alpha}
    + K(k)\right]
    </ndz_image>
    <br/> <br/>
    <ndz_image type="tex" name="equation2" alt="Off-axis field, radial component">
    B_r = B_0\frac{\gamma}{\pi\sqrt{Q}}\left[E(k)\frac{1+\alpha^2+\beta^2}{Q-4\alpha}
    - K(k)\right]
    </ndz_image>
  <p>
    <b>B</b> is the magnetic field, in teslas, at any point in 
    space that isn't on the current loop.  It is equal to the sum of two 
    field components:
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>B<sub>x</sub></b> the magnetic field component that is aligned with
    the coil axis and
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>B<sub>r</sub></b> the magnetic field component that is in a radial 
    direction.
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>i</b> is the current in the wire, in amperes.
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>a</b> is the radius of the current loop.
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>x</b> is the distance, on axis, from the center of the current loop
    to the field measurement point.
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>r</b> is the radial distance from the axis of the current loop to the
    field measurement point.
  </p>
  <p>
    <ndz_image type="tex" name="equation3" alt="definitions">
      \alpha=\frac{r}{a} \text{\hspace{20pt},\hspace{20pt} }
      \beta=\frac{x}{a} \text{ \hspace{20pt},\hspace{20pt} }
      \gamma=\frac{x}{r} 
    </ndz_image>
  </p>
  <p>
    <ndz_image type="tex" name="equation4" alt="definitions">
      Q = \left[(1+\alpha)^2+\beta^2\right]
    </ndz_image>
  </p>
  <p>
    <ndz_image type="tex" name="equation5" alt="definitions">
      k=\sqrt{\frac{4\alpha}{Q}}
    </ndz_image>
  </p>
  <p>
  <b><em>K(k)</em></b> is the complete elliptic integral function, of the first kind.<br/>
  </p>
  <p>
  <b><em>E(k)</em></b> is the complete elliptic integral function, of the second kind.<br/>
  </p>
  <p>
  Note that the argument to K and E is shown here as the modulus &quot;k&quot;.
  Other valid arguments are the parameter &quot;m&quot; (where m = k<sup>2</sup>)
  and the modular angle &quot;&alpha;&quot; (where &alpha; = sin<sup>-1</sup>k).
  Substitute the argument that is appropriate for the mathematical tool you are 
  using.
  </p>
  <p>
  <b>B<sub>o</sub></b> is the magnetic field at the center of the coil 
  (i&mu;<sub>o</sub>/2a)
  </p>
  <p>
  <b>&mu;<sub>o</sub></b> is the permeability constant (1.26x10<sup>-6</sup> H/m or
  4&pi;x10<sup>-7</sup>).
  </p>
  <p>
  As always, units of linear dimension (a) and magnetic field (B) are 
  adjustable by using an appropriate value for the permeability constant.
  </p>
  </ndz_section>  
  <ndz_section title="Elliptic Integrals and Other Problems">
  <p>  
  &quot;What is an elliptic integral function?&quot; you say. My calculator
  doesn't have one of those! 
  </p>
  <p>
  If you want to use the formulas on this page, you'll need to be able to 
  find complete elliptic integrals of the first and second kind for values 
  of k between 0 and 1. Please see this 
  <a href="https://www.wakari.io/sharing/bundle/ericdennison/magnets/Off%20Axis%20Field%20of%20a%20Current%20Loop.ipynb">iPython Notebook</a> for code examples in Python that you can duplicate
  and experiment with.
  </p>
  <p>
Credits
The formulas on this page are adapted from:

SOME USEFUL INFORMATION FOR THE DESIGN OF AIR-CORE SOLENOIDS by D.Bruce Montgomery and J. Terrell., published November, 1961, under Air Force Contract AF19(604)-7344. 

Montgomery and Terrell, in turn, credit:

STATIC AND DYNAMIC ELECTRICITY by W.R. Smythe, p. 266, McGraw-Hill, New York, 1950.
  </p>
  </ndz_section>
</ndz_document>
